<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning | Ishaan Rawal</title>
    <link>https://israwal.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://israwal.github.io/tag/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Machine Learning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://israwal.github.io/media/icon_hue5d671e0b768c50a6d08d5b4f04cff0f_40307_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Video Reconstruction From fMRI Signals</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/brain_video/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/brain_video/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Ongoing (Since Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am being advised by &lt;a href=http://userpage.fu-berlin.de/rmcichy/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Radoslaw Martin Cichy&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=https://www.ewi-psy.fu-berlin.de/en/einrichtungen/arbeitsbereiche/neural_dyn_of_vis_cog/index.html
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Neural Dynamics of Visual Cognition Lab&lt;/a&gt;, Freie Universität Berlin) and &lt;a href=http://www.cvai.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/team.html
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Gemma Roig&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=http://www.cvai.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Computer Vision and Artificial Intelligence Lab&lt;/a&gt;, Goethe University) for my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis. We are decoding and reconstructing the  natural videos from brain fMRI signals using deep learning. I am extending the &lt;a href=https://dmitryulyanov.github.io/deep_image_prior
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Deep Image Prior&lt;/a&gt; and using it to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constrain the reconstructions in the natural and temporal coherence manifold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the representations in Deep Neural Networks and brain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probe unlearnt priors by the virtue of the architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Random Fourier Implicit Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/fourier_implicit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/fourier_implicit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Jul 2020 - Oct 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with &lt;a href=http://peterwonka.net/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Peter Wonka&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=https://cemse.kaust.edu.sa/vcc
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Visual Computing Center&lt;/a&gt;, KAUST. I worked on improving the PSNR values for neural implicit
representations for Images. Building on the Random Fourier Features, I experimented with different
approaches — neighbourhood-aware representation, hierarchically scaled representation and multi-step
representations (with differential RGB images). With heirarchical scaling, we were able to imrpove the PSNR
values as much as 0.3 for some cases. However, large-scale experiments are required to substantiate the claims.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis Of Long-Distance Linked Selection In Indian Variants Of SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (June 2020 - Sept 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was done virtually during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, in collaboration with &lt;a href=http://arunsethuraman.weebly.com/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Arun Sethuraman&lt;/a&gt;, California State University, San Marcos. Long-range mutations are not well studied in evolutionary biology. We hypothesised that associations in long-range mutations give more reasons to inspect causality in SARS-CoV-2. This would help to analyse the trajectory of mutations of the virus. We analysed 1,200 whole genome sequences and identified 14 significant non-synonymous mutations. The association rules were mined using the apriori algorithm, and their stability was analysed using homology modelling. This was the first-ever data-driven analysis of long-range viral mutations. We found two clusters of significant non-synonymous mutations and analysed the intra and inter-cluster rules (figure above).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervertebral Disc Segmentation Using U-Net</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/disc_segment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/disc_segment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (May 2020 - Jul 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was completed as part of my summer internship at &lt;a href=https://orthobiomech.ethz.ch/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Laboratory for Orthopaedic Biomechanics&lt;/a&gt;, ETH Zurich, under the guidance of Dr. Jonas Widmer. I contributed to the image segmentation component of a larger pipeline for automatic analysis of spine MRI to identify spinal defects. Particularly, I was involved in the segmentation of intervertebral disc. I compared different variants of U-Net (viz. vanilla, skip connection, inception modules etc.) for the task. The best model (inception U-Net with skip connections) achieved a dice score of 94.1%, and the overall segmentation pipeline scored 91.8%, which is competitive with the state-of-the-art approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
