<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Other | Ishaan Rawal</title>
    <link>https://israwal.github.io/tag/other/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://israwal.github.io/tag/other/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Other</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://israwal.github.io/media/icon_hue5d671e0b768c50a6d08d5b4f04cff0f_40307_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Other</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/tag/other/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graph Compaction Algorithm For Novel de-novo Genome Assembler</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/genome_assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/genome_assembly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Jan 2021 - May 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a student researcher at &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/computerscience/AdvancedDataAnalyticsParallelTechnologiesLaboratory
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Advanced Data Analytics and Parallel Technologies (ADAPT) Lab, BITS Pilani&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=https://universe.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/poonam/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Poonam Goyal&lt;/a&gt;. We are working on biological &lt;a href=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sequence_assembly
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;sequence assembly&lt;/a&gt;, which is an NP-hard string reconstruction problem. We are building a novel de-novo short-read genome assembler to reconstruct the DNA contigs efficiently. The proposed assembler is being built with distributed and hierarchical data structures and using intermediaries- unitigs to avoid the bottlenecks in the pipeline. We harness overlap, and paired-end information along with some novel features to extend the unitigs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Structure Of Novel Heavy Metal Complexes For Cancer Detection</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/heavy_metal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/heavy_metal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Aug 2020 - Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cancer Diagnostic Tool Project is a collaboration between the Department of Biological Sciences and the Department of Chemistry, BITS Pilani. As a part of the initiative, in-house developed backbones of the novel heavy metal complex were being explored to develop affordable (less than 1 USD) and portable cancer diagnostic tools. These heavy metal complexes rely on Aggregation-Induced Emission (AIE) mechanism for detection. Under the guidance of &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/shiba/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Shibasish Chowdhury&lt;/a&gt;, my job was to find the optimal structure of the complexes against EphB4 (a cancer biomarker) using molecular docking. The results from my in-silico study are being translated to the wet-lab work to test and further optimise the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Modelling Of Gene Regulatory Networks Using cs-PBN</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/pbn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/pbn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Aug 2020 - Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/rajeshk/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Rajesh Kumar&lt;/a&gt;, Formal Methods Lab, BITS Pilani, I theoretically showed the close ties between the two popular Boolean models of stochasticity — Stochasticity in Nodes (&lt;a href=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17543998/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;SIN&lt;/a&gt;) and Stochasticity in Function (&lt;a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2687968/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;SIF&lt;/a&gt;). This was done by proving both the models as a special instance of the generic framework of context-sensitive Probabilistic Boolean Networks, modelled using discrete-time Markov chains. We also attempted to understand the stable attractor dynamics of probabilistic networks and their physical implications as different phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis Of Long-Distance Linked Selection In Indian Variants Of SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (June 2020 - Sept 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was done virtually during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, in collaboration with &lt;a href=http://arunsethuraman.weebly.com/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Arun Sethuraman&lt;/a&gt;, California State University, San Marcos. Long-range mutations are not well studied in evolutionary biology. We hypothesised that associations in long-range mutations give more reasons to inspect causality in SARS-CoV-2. This would help to analyse the trajectory of mutations of the virus. We analysed 1,200 whole genome sequences and identified 14 significant non-synonymous mutations. The association rules were mined using the apriori algorithm, and their stability was analysed using homology modelling. This was the first-ever data-driven analysis of long-range viral mutations. We found two clusters of significant non-synonymous mutations and analysed the intra and inter-cluster rules (figure above).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
