<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Ishaan Rawal</title>
    <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://israwal.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://israwal.github.io/media/icon_hue5d671e0b768c50a6d08d5b4f04cff0f_40307_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel de-novo Short-Read Genome Assembler</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/genome_assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/genome_assembly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Ongoing (Since Jan 2021)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working as a student researcher at &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/computerscience/AdvancedDataAnalyticsParallelTechnologiesLaboratory
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Advanced Data Analytics and Parallel Technologies (ADAPT) Lab, BITS Pilani&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=https://universe.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/poonam/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Poonam Goyal&lt;/a&gt;. We are working on biological &lt;a href=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sequence_assembly
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;sequence assemby&lt;/a&gt; which is an NP-hard string reconstruction problem. We are building a novel de-novo short-read genome assembler to reconstruct the DNA contigs efficiently. The proposed assembler is being built with distributed and hierarchical data structures and using intermediaries- unitigs to avoid the bottlenecks in the pipeline. We harness overlap and paired-end information along with some novel features to extend the unitigs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Video Reconstruction From Brain Activity</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/brain_video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/brain_video/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Ongoing (Since Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working with &lt;a href=http://userpage.fu-berlin.de/rmcichy/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Radoslaw Martin Cichy&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=https://www.ewi-psy.fu-berlin.de/en/einrichtungen/arbeitsbereiche/neural_dyn_of_vis_cog/index.html
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Neural Dynamics of Visual Cognition Lab&lt;/a&gt;, Freie Universität Berlin) and &lt;a href=http://www.cvai.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/team.html
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Gemma Roig&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=http://www.cvai.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Computer Vision and Artificial Intelligence Lab&lt;/a&gt;, Goethe University) to decode and reconstruct the features of natural videos from brain fMRI signals using Deep Learning. We are using deep neural network activations as a proxy to map the fMRI features to the video space to decode, understand and compare the hierarchical and selective representation of features in the brain and neural network. We are also exploring end-to-end models which can produce both encodings and decodings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Modelling Of Gene Regulatory Networks Using Formal Methods</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/pbn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/pbn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Aug 2020 - Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/rajeshk/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Rajesh Kumar&lt;/a&gt;, Formal Methods Lab, BITS Pilani, we theoretically showed the close ties between the two popular Boolean models of stochasticity- Stochasticity in Nodes (&lt;a href=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17543998/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;SIN&lt;/a&gt;) and Stochasticity in Function (&lt;a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2687968/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;SIF&lt;/a&gt;). This was done by proving both the models as a special instance of the generic framework- context sensitive probabilistic Boolean networks which are modelled using discrete time markov chains. We also attempted to understand the stable attractor dynamics of probabiltic networks and their physical implications as different phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Structure Of Novel Heavy Metal Complexes For Cancer Detection</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/heavy_metal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/heavy_metal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (Aug 2020 - Dec 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cancer Diagnostic Tool Project is a collaboration between the Department of Biological Sciences and Department fo Chemsitry, BITS Pilani. As a part of the initiative, in-house developed backbones of novel heavy metal complex were being explored to develop affordable (less than 1 USD) and portable cancer diagnostic tools. These heavy metal complexes rely on Aggregation-Induced Emission (AIE) mechanism for detection. My job, under the guidance of &lt;a href=https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/pilani/shiba/profile
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Shibasish Chowdhury&lt;/a&gt;, was to find the optimal structure of the complexes against EphB4 (a cancer biomarker) using molecular docking. The results from my in-silico study are being translated to the wet-lab work to test and further optimise the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis Of Long-Distance Linked Selection In Indian Variants Of SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/covid_genome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (June 2020 - Sept 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was done virtually during the fist wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, in collaboration with &lt;a href=http://arunsethuraman.weebly.com/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Prof. Arun Sethuraman&lt;/a&gt;, California State University, San Marcos. Long range mutations are not well studied in evolutionary biology. We hypothesized that associations in long-range mutations gives more reasons to inspect causality in SARS-CoV-2. This would help to analyze the trajectory of mutations of the virus. We analyzed 1,200 full genome sequences and identified 14 significant non-synonymous mutations. The association rules were mined using apriori algorithm and their individual stability was analyzed using homology modelling. This was the first ever data-driven analysis of viral long-range mutations. We found out two clusters of significant non-synonymous mutations and analyzed the intra and inter-cluster rules (figure above). We presented our work at the virtual poster presentation at COVID-19 Dynamics and Evolution Virtual Conference, organised by UC San Diego School of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervertebral Disc Segmentation Using U-Net</title>
      <link>https://israwal.github.io/project/disc_segment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://israwal.github.io/project/disc_segment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;: Completed (May 2020 - Jul 2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was completed as part of my summer internship at &lt;a href=https://orthobiomech.ethz.ch/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Laboratory for Orthopaedic Biomechanics&lt;/a&gt;, ETH Zurich, under the guidance of &lt;a href=https://biomech.ethz.ch/the-institute/people/person-detail.html?persid&amp;#61;172198
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Dr. Jonas Widmer&lt;/a&gt;. I contributed to the image segmentation component of a larger pipeline for automatic analysis of spine MRI to indentify spinal defects. Particularly, I was involved in segmentation of intervertebral disc. I compared different variants of U-Net (viz. vanilla, skip connection, inception modules etc) for the task. The best model (inception U-Net with skip connections) achieved a dice score of 94.1% and the overall segmentation pipeline scored 91.8%, which is competent with the state-of-the-art apporoaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
